{
  "reference_number": "10953",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I'd expect international negotiations to continue over how our world can best respond to the climate-change issues; I'd expect our\n government to be an active and constructive participant in these negotiations; and I'd expect our government to adjust its laws and\n targets to move toward the forefront (rather than be a laggard, as at present) of international responses. For example: it is feasible to\n\n distinguish agricultural emissions of methane from \"fossil fuel\" emissions of methane and also from other major emission sources\n (e.g. landfills); there may be sound scientific reasons to make this distinction when calculating our world's progress toward stabilising\n\n (and then reducing!) our atmospheric CO2; other nations may or may not agree that this is appropriate (and it would certainly be in\n NZ's narrow self-interest to privilege agricultural emissions of methane over other sources); and our laws and targets should adjust\n as required to reflect any international consensus on this particular issue."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "? I don't understand how it would be possible for any Government to create a budget that cannot be changed by any later\n Government (or even by itself!), except by enshrining it in a constitutional document -- and that's far out of scope for this\n consultation!"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Our current ETS is an embarrassment on the international stage, and domestically for anyone who believes (as I do) that its\nincreasingly-thin coating of greenwash is an entirely inadequate response. I think the most important role for the Climate Change\nCommission would be to advocate for adequate & appropriate responses by all NZ actors: governmental, for-profit organisations, not-\n\nfor-profit organisations, and individuals."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    }
  ]
}
